we keep being handed wonderful
opportunities to recognize that we have
a problem
and we keep finding increasingly
sophisticated ways to deny that we have
a problem
um we need to notice we have a problem
and we need to take the time
to really perceive that
and really take it as our problem
like not their problem not some pick
your poison
yeah you know point the finger and
create the appropriate disparagement
that fits your particular perspective on
these
things yep um nope nope it's in fact my
problem i'm going to take full
responsibility for
where we are which means by the way
understanding what it means to take
responsibility
i can't be an activist because activism
is false responsibility it's
expecting that you can do stuff you
can't actually do well what can you take
responsibility for
well the first thing you can take
responsibility for is participating at
all
in the kind of mind
what i call a sense maker the kind of
sense maker
that is game a
and the game a sense maker is a kind
it's not the only one that exists in
potential
there are other examples um but it's the
generator function
if you always find yourself trying to
figure out how to solve
problems from the game a toolkit
using the game a sense maker then all
you're doing is playing game a
now that turns out to be daunting and
for a lot of people
the game the sort of the story stops
there um
although to be perfectly frank for the
vast majority of people
it actually wouldn't be that hard to
shift but because of the way the human
beings
relate to each other it ends up being
how do i say this right
most people look to other people to
figure out what the right way to respond
to the world is
we're a mimetic creature right we're a
memetic creature
right so it's
the sort the kind of people who for
whatever remember that we ever see that
big great photograph
of like a nuremberg style rally and
there's like
a hundred thousand nazis like saluting
and one dude standing there folding his
arms
he's not seeing it now you haven't seen
it oh it's great you should get it and
like
you put it up yep because the question
the point is
if you had 10 people fold in their arms
the whole rally falls apart because at
the end of the day people are like sick
they're like
feeling out into their environment okay
what is the right way to respond to
what's happening
and if they're just getting signals that
are always pointing in the same
direction okay i guess that's what it is
but there are some people who for
whatever reason because of their life
experience
because of their genotype uh because of
secure circumstance
are in a position to not respond
in the self-reinforcing feedback loop
of their social milieu if there's enough
of them
that are signaling something different
and they're signaling that something
different with
some coherence meaning that it's kind of
showing up as the same kind of signal
then you begin to get a shift and it
gives everybody else an orientation
towards what right action might feel
like
it might look like um
so that's how you begin to make the move
from game to game b